<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Doubts concerning the Roman infallibility I. whether the Church of Rome believe it, II. whether Jesus Christ or his Apostles ever recommended it, III. whether the primitive church knew or used that way of deciding controversie.</title>
            <author>Maurice, Henry, 1648-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50334</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1362</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15937</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13148159</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13148159</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98083</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50334)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98083)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 428:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Doubts concerning the Roman infallibility I. whether the Church of Rome believe it, II. whether Jesus Christ or his Apostles ever recommended it, III. whether the primitive church knew or used that way of deciding controversie.</title>
                  <author>Maurice, Henry, 1648-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for James Adamson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Henry Maurice. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Advertisements: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Infallibility.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:98083:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur, <hi>Hic Liber, cui Titulus,</hi> Doubts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Roman</hi> Infallibility, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>May 17. 1688.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Guil. Needham, <hi>R.R. in Ch. P. ac D. D.</hi> Wilhelmo <hi>Archiep.</hi> Cant. <hi>a Sacris Domeſt.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98083:1"/>
            <p>DOUBTS Concerning the <hi>Roman Infallibility:</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>I. Whether the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> Believe it.</item>
                  <item>II. Whether Jeſus Chriſt or his Apoſtles ever Recommended it.</item>
                  <item>III. Whether the Primitive Church Knew or Uſed that Way of Deciding Controverſie.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>James Adamſon,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's Church-Yard,</hi> MDCLXXXVIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:98083:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98083:2"/>
            <head>DOUBTS Concerning the <hi>Roman Infallibility.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Advantage of having an Infallible Judge to Determine Controverſies of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is ſo Viſible, that thoſe, who for their Lives cannot bring themſelves to believe, Either that there is ſuch a Judge on Earth; or that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is ſo Qualifyed, cannot yet but wiſh, That there were one exempt from the common Frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Miſtaking. For who would not be deſirous of being releaſed from the Toyl of Examining every Point of his Faith by Scripture and Tradition, when af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all, the Iſſue is uncertain? Who can envy himſelf the Bleſſedneſs of being raiſed above all Apprehenſion and Jealouſie of being Miſtaken in (that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns him above all things) the Religion and Faith by which he is to be Saved? When therefore we ſee ſo great a part of Chriſtians Diſputing againſt their own Wiſhes, and rejecting all Pretenders to Infallibility; it is a ſtrong Preſumption, That the Truth of ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility is not ſo Evident and Viſible, as the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage that flows from the Suppoſition of it. For it is commonly more than half way towards Believing a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98083:3"/>thing to be True, to have a deſire that it ſhould be ſo.</p>
            <p>The common Objection of the Force of Prejudice againſt Evident Truth, can have no place here; for if there be any Prejudice in this Caſe, it is For, and not Againſt Infallibility. For thoſe of our Church, who have oppoſed this Pretence with greateſt Diligence and Succeſs, have taken care to prevent this Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by profeſſing more than an ordinary Deſire that it might be true. The Lord <hi>Falkland,</hi> a Perſon of great Honour as well as of Learning and Acuteneſs, declares, <q>That if God would leave it to him, Which Tenet ſhould be True, he would Chuſe that Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility ſhould, rather than the contrary.</q> Mr. <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingworth,</hi> who thought once to have found out the Infallible Judge, (but lo it was a Dream) makes this Solemn Profeſſion: <q>For my part, (ſo he ſpeaks) I know I am as Willing and Deſirous, That the Biſhop or Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould be Infallible (provided I might know it) as they are to be ſo eſteemed.</q> Dr. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> doubts not to profeſs the ſame good Inclination,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi>'s Preface to his Defence of the Lord <hi>Falkland.</hi>
               </note> in the Name of all Proteſtants. <q>If there were (ſays he) but one Wiſh offered to each Man among us; it would certainly, with a full Conſent, be laid out on this one Treaſure, the ſetting up of one Catholick Umpire or Days-man, ſome Viſible, Infallible De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cider of Controverſie.</q> It is very hard that Perſons ſo well diſpoſed, ſhould not be able to attain to the Belief of ſo Eaſing and Commodious a Principle; for, beſides their Good-will, they wanted neither Learning nor Diligence, nor Judgment, to make themſelve Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of their Deſire: But it ſeems it is not given to all to Believe Infallibility; and poſſibly the great Talents of theſe Perſons might be no ſmall Hindrance to their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98083:3"/>
            <p>Now, ſince we ſtill Profeſs to have the ſame De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and Fondneſs of Believing Infallibility upon good Grounds, with the Perſons above-mentioned; in Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, Reverend Fathers of the Miſſion, it will be ſome Diſparagement to your Glorious Undertaking of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, to ſuffer Men ſo well Diſpoſed, to languiſh out their Lives with a Fruitleſs Deſire of finding the Infallible Judge, and at laſt to Dye without that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: For you certainly, or none, the Glory of our Converſion is reſerved, for the Proof of the Infallible Church is your peculiar Province; and to do you Right, you keep ſo cloſe to it, as ſeldom to ſuffer your Study or Underſtanding to paſs the Bounds of this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, humbly content with this Summary Creed; <hi>I Believe the Infallible Church.</hi> If therefore, you have any Demonſtrations, or Infallible Arguments, or Weighty Reaſons, we beſeech you to produce them, deny not your ſelves the Glory of Convincing us, for we long to be your Conqueſt. But then, to prevent a Needleſs Trouble, we are obliged to let you know, That the Old Arguments have been all Weighed with great Care, and found Light, and it will not be for your Reputation to offer us the ſame Bad Mony for Payment, that has been refuſed a hundred times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. You may, if you pleaſe, call theſe Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Unanſwerable Things; but for our part, we, after the moſt Diligent Examination, can find No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in them but Noiſe, that may perhaps create Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance to ſome Weak Perſons, unacquainted with Sophiſtry, but ſerve only for Sport to the more Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. They are like the Clock of a Death watch, a poor little Worm ſcarce viſible, that may Fright, it may be, Melancholy or Timorous Perſons, but in Truth ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie nothing. Or like the Dwarf of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98083:4"/>by <hi>Suetonius,</hi> That was but ſeventeen Pound Weight, not two Foot High, and of a Prodigious Voice; only this Creature had ſome Subſtance, tho' but very little: But the Evidences for the Infallibility, hitherto produced, will not turn the Scale againſt a Feather.</p>
            <p>Now to give you ſome Comfort for your Unſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Practice upon Minds ſo well diſpoſed, I will make bold to lay before you ſome Inſtances of your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and Companions of the ſame Misfortune. The Doctors of the Stage, whom Scurrilous Men call Mountebanks, proclaim themſelves Infallible in their Way, they make Liberal Offers of Infallible Medicines, of never-failing Remedies, or Certain and Never-err<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Operations. Yet a great part of the World, and reputed the Wiſeſt, paſs by theſe great Diſpenſers of Health, theſe Confident Enſurers of Life and Longe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, and depend upon ſuch Modeſt Phyſitians as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare themſelves Fallible, and do not Diſſemble their Diffidence of the ſucceſs of their Applications. Yet theſe Patients have as ſtrong a Deſire of Eaſe and Health, as any of their Neighbours, and would give all the World for a really Infallible Operator.</p>
            <p>There are other Men Bold enough, to Pretend, That they have the Secret of making Gold. This they affirm with ſo much Aſſurance, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> cannot ſhew more in her Claim of Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. Nay they have their Demonſtrations, their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable Reaſons, their certain Grounds: And at laſt, for an Irreſiſtible Inducement to believe, they have their Revelations too. Now as well as Men love Gold, there are not many that will Believe the Pretence, or be perſwaded to ſend their Baſer Metals to undergo the Improvement of this Golden Tranſubſtantiation.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98083:4"/>
            <p>I am loth to impute this general Infidelity, either in regard of the Infallible Judge, or of the Infallible Operators, wholly to the want of competent Proof on the Side of the Pretenders; the greedineſs of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving what Men have a mind ſhould be true, ſeems to me ſufficient to Counterballance that Defect, and to diſpoſe Men to accept very ſlender Evidence. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beſides want of Proof, there muſt be ſome other powerful hindrance, ſome viſible and obvious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions of Impoſture, that immediately ſtop our eaſineſs and forwardneſs of Believing. For,</p>
            <p n="1">I. It is ſtrong preſumption of a Cheat, when Men are obſerv'd to be utterly deſtitute of all thoſe great good things they pretend to have in their power to beſtow. Who can have regard to the Vapouring of a Mountebank upon the Stage, that has ſeen the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of that Pretender languiſhing without relief under the moſt Common and Curable Diſeaſes? Who can endure the Cant of a Begger about the Secret of Making Gold? Or have the Patience to ſee a Man who has the <hi>Indies</hi> within the power of his Art, if his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence were not a Lye, condeſcend to Beg or Borrow a ſmall piece of Mony to ſave himſelf from Starving? It is no otherwiſe with the Pretence of Infallibility; our deſire of believing it, lies under the check of this Preſumption. For the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that offers us the Benefit of her Infallibility, to remove the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences we have with her, or among our ſelves, is found to make no uſe of it in her own Occaſions, to heal thoſe Differences that ariſe within her own Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. The Diſputes between the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> and <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicans</hi> are of great Importance, yet the Infallible Judge all the while they depended, did never think fit to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98083:5"/>Interpoſe. This Doctrin of Infallibility it ſelf, is doubtleſs fundamental, and the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided about it, ſome aſcribing it to the Pope, others to a Council; yet the Infallible Judge is ſo ſhy of uſing his Gift, as to reſtrain it, when it is moſt neceſſary for the Manifeſtation and Defence of its own ſelf. If the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> has an Infallible Judgment, it has indeed a wonderful Gift, but to the leaſt purpoſe or ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect that can be imagined. For in deciding the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies of thoſe that pretend to believe it, the Church does not think fit to uſe it. And thoſe that do not believe it, can receive no benefit by its Definitions; and yet it is to theſe only that it thinks fit to define.</p>
            <p n="2">II. If the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> were Infallible, we cannot but think ſhe would afford her People Infallible Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; <hi>i.e.</hi> ſhe would take care that her Catechiſms, her Liturgies, and her Sermons, ſhould be Infallibly true Doctrins. But if you will enquire how this Infallible Church teaches her Diſciples, you will find, that her Catechiſms were Compoſed by Fallible Men, and are Expounded by Men as Fallible as they. If you go to her Sermons, you hear the words of Fallible Monks, or Curates, or ſometimes of Biſhops, who may be He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, and Preach damnable Doctrins. If you go to her Publick Offices, there you meet with Forms made by they know not whom; there you will hear Lections of Uncertain Authority, taken out of Legends, and the Writings of Men that either were or might be miſtaken. Therefore when ſome of the Advocates of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, are preſs'd by any Objections taken from the Publick Offices, they decline the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and diſpenſe with themſelves for maintaining them as the Unerring Belief of the Church. For the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98083:5"/>Infallible Church, forſooth does not ſpeak to the People in theſe Offices. This we readily accept, but then we deſire ſome reaſon may be given, why this Church, being (as they pretend) Infallible, does not think fit to inſtruct her People infallibly in her Liturgies or Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, ſince thoſe are the ordinary ways by which the People are Inſtructed? And why ſhe expoſes the Souls of Men to the poſſible danger of Miſcarrying by the ignorance or perverſeneſs of her Fallible Prieſts, when it is in her power to prevent all this by her own Infallible voice, ſpeaking in Homilies, or Catechiſms, or Liturgies, or other Authentick Books, all as true as the Bible? Wherefore all things conſider'd, I conceive our Opinion, That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> may Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, is leſs diſhonourable to her than theirs, who would flatter her to fancy her ſelf Infallible. For we leave her a good Excuſe why ſhe does not give her Children Infallible Inſtruction, Becauſe ſhe has no ſuch Privilege; whereas her Flatterers leave her inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable, for not doing that which they confeſs ſhe does not do, and yet contend ſhe is able to do. Which will certainly leave her in the Opinion of all Impartial Judges, moſt unworthy of ſo great a Truſt as that of Infallibility.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Although the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks in their Diſputes with Us, are very forward to appeal to the Infallible Judge, becauſe he is their own; yet when they miſtruſt that their own Opinions are in danger of being Condemn'd by the ſame Judge, they make uſe of all means to prevent or decline his Judgment. We have ſeveral Inſtances to this purpoſe in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> which I think has moſt voices in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church for being Infallible. But I will content my
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98083:6"/>ſelf with one only, and that is the Debate about the Immaculate Conception of the Virgin. When the Article of Original Sin came to defin'd, it ſeemed ſcarce to be avoided, but that this of the Conception muſt be involv'd. For if they defin'd in General, without Exception, That <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sin paſs'd upon All, the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin would be concluded, and the <hi>Franciſcan</hi> Doctrin Condemn'd: But if ſhe were Excepted, and declared Pure from that Original Blemiſh, then the <hi>Dominicans</hi> would be Condemn'd. Be it ſo; but why ſhould either Side be afraid of an Infallible Judge? Why ſhould they not by conſent ſubmit their Diſputes and their Opinions, to that which had clearer Light, and could not be miſtaken? They had wrangled enough about it in the Dark, &amp; according to their Uncertain and Fallible Judgment, now an opportunity offer'd it ſelf, of letting all Sides know the Truth, and of putting an End to that tedious Controverſie. But nothing could be done for want of Faith, and Reſignation to the Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Judge: I cannot believe ſo hardly of the <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicans,</hi> as that they were unwilling to know the certain Truth of the Matter; and if they had been in their Conſcience perſuaded, that whatſoever the Majority of the Council had defin'd, muſt be Truth, it cannot be conceived why they ſhould be ſo Induſtrious to avoid a Sentence. They ſaw indeed a Majority on the other Side; but then it was a Majority of Private Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which if they were in the wrong, muſt change, when they came to define as a Council, or elſe fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well all Council-Infallibility. But the <hi>Dominicans</hi> it ſeems would not truſt that, and I do not blame them; but then we appeal to their Equity, and deſire that they would not put upon us that Infallible Judge, to whom they are ſo loth to ſubmit their own Opinions.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:98083:6"/>
            <p>But let theſe <hi>Dominicans</hi> be as reſtive as they pleaſe, and unwilling to have this Point Decided, yet the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jority of the Council, which is to ſome an Infallible Judge, they, methinks, ſhould not be afraid to declare the whole Truth; for they ſurely could not miſtruſt their own Infallibility, and as little could they Queſtion the Acquieſcence and Submiſſion of all good Catholicks, yet theſe had Scruples, and could not ſpeak out, for they had received a Caution from <hi>Rome,</hi> whence their Spirit of Defining came, <hi>That they ſhould by no means Meddle with that Controverſie that depended between Catholicks, which might occaſion a Schiſm:</hi> How! For a General Council to determine a Controverſie between Catholicks, would it be to expoſe the Church to the Danger of Schiſm? Where then is their Belief of Infallibility? Where is their Reſignation to the Decrees of the Church? Or to what Purpoſe is Infallibility given, if it cannot be Exerciſed for fear of Offence, and giving occaſion to Schiſm? We are told, That the only Remedy againſt Hereſie and Schiſm is the Determination of the Church, and we are preſſed to forſake our Religion, becauſe the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> has condemned it; whereas, in Confidence between Pope and Council, we find that their Catholicks would leave them for that very Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which they uſe to Convert us, <hi>i. e.</hi> If they durſt Condemn their Opinions, as they have done ours.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid indeed, That this Article of the Immaculate Conception is not of Faith, and therefore needs not to be decided, and if it were, the Deciſion of the Church may not be Infallibly True, becauſe the Promiſe of Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Aſſiſtance extends only to Matters of Faith. I ſhould be better content with this Anſwer, if I could be ſatisfy'd once, What is of Faith, and what is not: How comes Invocation of Saints, Worſhipping of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98083:7"/>Images and Purgatory, to be of Faith, and this not? It cannot be ſaid, Becauſe the Church has determin'd thoſe Points and not this. For, before I enquired, Why the Church would not determine this, and it was given me for a Reaſon, That it was not of Faith. Or is it becauſe it does not ſeem to be of ſo great moment in it ſelf? This cannot be pretended; for Matters of leſs Moment have been declared to be of Faith: For In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, The Perpetual Virginity of the Bleſſed Virgin, is an Article, in it ſelf, of leſs Moment than this of the Immaculate Conception; for he that denies that the Mother of our Lord always continued a Virgin, makes her leſs Perfect in the Opinion of ſome, but not Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal in the Judgment of any: For if ſhe had enjoy'd the Liberty of Wedlock ſhe had not ſinned. But he that affirms her to be Conceived in Sin, if ſhe knew no Sin, is a Falſe and Blaſphemous Accuſer, and does her real Diſhonour. Yet <hi>Helvidius,</hi> and ſome others, that denyed her Perpetual Virginity, are Hereticks; the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> that charge her with Original Sin, and that Unjuſtly, according to the Opinion of the major part of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> if we may believe <hi>Pallavicini,</hi> and of the preſent <hi>Roman Church,</hi> are ſtill Good Catholicks, and the Queſtion muſt not be Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly Decided againſt them for fear of Schiſm.</p>
            <p>But one of the greateſt Hindrances of our Belief of Infallibility is to ſee, That thoſe who affirm that ſuch a Priviledge belongs to their Church, cannot agree where to place it: Some are for the Pope, ſome for a General Council, ſome for the Church Diffuſive; now if but one of theſe Competitors be Infallible, of three Parties, into which the Roman Church is divided up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Queſtion, there are two againſt him, and as very Hereticks as we. If all the three be Infallible,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98083:7"/>then all the Roman Church is in a Dangerous Error, for of this Trinity of Infallible Judges, no Party be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves but one, to the Excluſion of the other two. Nor can they Reproach us with rejecting all the three, for we allow the Church Diffuſive to be Infallible in a Senſe; that is, That there ſhall be always Perſons profeſſing the Subſtance of the Chriſtian Faith, only we do not make theſe Infallible Judges, nor reſolve our Faith into this Pious Opinion as into a firſt Principle. But we need not inſiſt upon this, for the Romaniſts themſelves confeſs, That the Church Diffuſive can be no Judge, and that no Controverſie in Religion was ever yet Decided by it. Now, while the Romaniſts are Diſagreed about their Infallible Judge, how can we believe that they have any? For ſurely, If God had appointed ſuch a Judge, he had rendred him ſo Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous and Remarkable, that every one who was not wilfully Blind muſt have Diſcerned him, elſe there could be no Uſe of him, and inſtead of Ending Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, he would Serve only to Increaſe it, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming himſelf the Subject of a New Diſpute. For what Uſe, I pray, of an Infallible Judge that lies <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognito;</hi> or what benefit from that Infallibility that is Diſtracted between many and Endleſs Competitions? The Wiſdom of God is not wont to confer ſo great a Gift to ſo little purpoſe, and thoſe who concern the Divine Wiſdom in this Queſtion, by ſaying, That God had not made ſufficient Proviſion for his Church, if he had not made it Infallible, do not conſider, That while they Diſagree about this Infallibility, they overthrow their own Argument, and betray the Divine Wiſdom, after they had intereſted it in their Diſputes. When they pretend to be all agreed in this, That they Blieve the Pope and a General Council in conjunction to make
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98083:8"/>up one Infallible Compound, we have great Reaſon to ſuſpect, That what they ſay is not True, and that they do not believe it themſelves; for ſeveral have lived and dyed in their Communion, who publickly taught, That a Pope and General Council concurring, may err in the Faith, and were never Cenſur'd for this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: Beſides, it is as reaſonable to believe that two Cyphers joyned may make up a Summ, as that two Fallible Parties can make up one Infallible in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction. Or if theſe Parties are Infallible apart, they do but mock us when they talk of their Conjunction. But that they do not Believe their own Pretence, ſeems to me plain, Becauſe they take no Care to be always provided of this Infallible Compound. How can they believe a Pope and Council united to be the only Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Judge, and yet uſe no Means to bring them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther once in a hundred Years? The Council of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> when it had Decreed Councils to be Infallible, took Care to Act according to their Pretence; and therefore ordered Councils to be frequent, and provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt all thoſe Impediments which the Jealouſie of the Roman Court might oppoſe to their Deſign. But that Men ſhould believe that Infallibility of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment belongs to a certain Conjunction of Parties, and yet to be content they ſhould never meet, and to let Ages paſs without the leaſt Benefit of this Infallibility that was in their Power, is ſuch a Riddle that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes my Weak Faith, ſo Rank a Pretence as would turn the Stomach of a Phariſee. But if they pretend, That the State of the World and Circumſtances of Princes will permit ſuch Aſſemblies but ſeldom, they fall foul upon the Wiſdom of God, that ſhould leave the Infallibility of the Church at the Diſcretion of Temporal Princes, and make the very Being of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98083:8"/>Infallible Judge to depend upon the Diſpoſition of theſe either to Peace or War. If it be ſaid that ſuch frequent Aſſemblies will be very inconvenient to the Church Univerſal, they muſt be anſwered, That the Subſiſting of an Infallible Judge, is ſuch an Advantage to the Church, as will abundantly ſatisfie for all the Inconvenience that can be pretended: Beſides, who does not ſee that all this is meer Shift? for in <hi>Rome</hi> there are commonly more Prelates attending upon that Court, than have made up ſeveral of the General Councils, which are accounted Infallible. Yet after all, this Church that boaſts ſo much of her Infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and makes that the Ground of her Dominion over the Faith of all Chriſtians, when ſhe may eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive that that Judge, which ſhe pretends to be Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible, ſhould be alſo a ſtanding one and perpetual, is content to commit either to the Inquiſition, which was never pretended to be exempt from Error; or to Epiſcopal Vicars, who are generally no great Divines, the Power of Declaring Hereſie, and of Condemning to the Fire, Men by them Adjudged to be Hereticks, when all the while, theſe very Judges are no leſs ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Hereſie than the Poor Creatures on whom they pronounce their Sentence. And though a General Council, once in an Age or two, might correct the Errors of theſe Decrees, yet can they reſtore the Souls which they have ſlain, or raiſe again the Bodies which theſe Miſtaken Judges had reduced to Aſhes?</p>
            <p>The more we conſider this Pretence of Joyning Pope and Council to make up an Infallible Judge, the more our Suſpicions do increaſe, not only that thoſe who ſet up this Judge againſt us, do not Believe him Infallible themſelves, but that the very Parties ſet up are not ſatisfyed of the Goodneſs of their own Title:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98083:9"/>For if they were convinced, That the only Means of having the Chriſtian Faith without Danger of Miſtake, was by their joynt Inſtruction, they would ſurely have better Inclination one for the other than has appeared for theſe laſt Ages, and would be deſirous of more frequent Meeting. But who does not know how the Popes ſtand affected to a Council? ſince for ſome Ages they have taken Care to Expreſs their Good Will, by a yearly Excommunication of all thoſe who ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to Appeal to it, which the Council of <hi>Baſil</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares to be Hereſie: But let the <hi>Sorbon,</hi> and the Abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of that Council look to this Tender Point.</p>
            <p>It cannot be unknown to any that Reads, with what Difficulty the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> ſo much Magnifyed after its Diſſolution, was Obtained, or rather Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: What Inſtances the Emperor uſed, what Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity and Threats, and that could obtain nothing du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring one whole Pontificat, and yet no very ſhort one. All Prinees of that Communion joyned in the ſame Requeſt, but to little Purpoſe; <hi>Paul</hi> the Third ſhifted it off as long as he could, with Delays and Excuſes, and Affected Exceptions, and all the Tricks of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved Averſion, till at laſt abſolute Neceſſity did Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort it from him. If God had appointed that Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility ſhould be the Iſſue of this Conjunction, in all likelihood he had Prepared the Parties with Kinder Diſpoſitions towards one another: For when he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Preſervation of all Animal Kinds, by the Conjunction of Male and Female, he inſpired them with a Mutual Good-liking; but the Antipathy which Popes have for Councils, makes it very Improbable that their Agreement ſhould be the only Certain Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Means of Preſerving the Truth of the Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:98083:9"/>
            <p>But beſides the Unwillingneſs of theſe Parties to come together to be Infallible, the great Diſtruſt they have one of another, when Met, begets in us a farther Suſpicion that they themſelves are not fully perſuaded of this Infallibility, at leaſt that they have not the full Aſſurance of Divine Faith about it: Two Kings at an Interview, or two Oppoſite Generals in Time of War, cannot be more Jealous or more Scrupulouſly Cautious about the Condition of the Place, or the Number of Attendants. If there muſt be a Council, the Pope would be beſt content to have it within his own Dominion, or where he can Command. Poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſuch Aſſemblies may be moſt Infallible within S. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Patrimony, though the Poor Apoſtles were forced to meet in an Enemy's Country: But what matters it where they Meet, if the Pope and they are Infallibly aſſiſted? A Simple Man would expect, That two Tallies ſhould not Agree more exactly when joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, than theſe two Pieces of Infallibility, when they come to confer Notes; but the Councils of <hi>Conſtance</hi> and <hi>Baſil,</hi> and <hi>Piſa,</hi> will Inform us, That there may be a Diſagreement, and that too if either Side is to be believed about Matters of Faith. Theſe Old Jarrs made the Popes, who are the Standing Part of the Infallible Compound, very jealous of the other, which is but Occaſional. And therefore, when the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> ſate, the Popes that directed it, thought they could never have Security enough of its Good-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour: For firſt, They would by no Means allow it the Title of Repreſenting the Univerſal Church, leſt it ſhould pretend to Engroſs the Infallibility, as others had done; then it was ordered, That nothing ſhould be Propoſed for Debate in it but by the <hi>Popes Legates;</hi> Then the Summ of all Debates were to be ſent to <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:98083:10"/>and nothing to be Concluded without new Direction: And as if all this were not Sufficient, Care was taken that <hi>Italian</hi> Prelates ſhould be ſent thither in ſuch Numbers, as might carry it againſt all the reſt, and if any Acceſſion of Biſhops came from <hi>France</hi> or other Places beyond the Mountains, new Levies were made in <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſent immediately to <hi>Trent</hi> to obſerve the Motions of thoſe Strangers. Theſe <hi>Italians,</hi> it may be, have a nearer Capacity of being Infallible, and if Infallibility depend upon the Agreement of Pope and Council, it cannot be denyed, for I think it is more poſſible for them both to Miſtake by Conſent, than for a Synod compoſed of ſuch as theſe, to have any Difference with him that Sends and Pays them. But if the Popes had been of Opinion, That all Private Opinions and Engagements were to be Over-ruled by the Infallible Spirit of Councils, and that whatſoever they might have Promiſed for the Wages of Unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, like <hi>Balam,</hi> they could not pronounce other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than as God moved them: Surely their Holineſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes would have learned to be Wiſer, by the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Balack,</hi> than to have waſted their Treaſure to engage Men of Uncertain Suffrage, and at laſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Curſe, perhaps inſtead of a Bleſſing. This Way of Procuring an Infallible Sentence, is enough to deſtroy all the Credit and Authority of it: For the Oracles of Old quickly Sunk in their Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when the Gods, and their Officers condeſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to accept of Penſions.</p>
            <p>Now as the too wary Conduct of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church towards her own Members, ſeems to confeſs a diſtruſt of her own Infallibility; ſo the Unreaſonable Confidence which ſhe uſes towards us, begets in us a juſt Suſpicion that ſhe is in the wrong, and is not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98083:10"/>Inſenſible of it. For it is a ſign of a very bad Cauſe, when thoſe concern'd to Defend it, are unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to enter into its Merits; and inſtead of that, only bluſter and ſtand upon their Privilege; inſtead of Maintaining it by Law and Reaſon, declare that they are to give Law, and not to ſubmit to any; and that whatſoever they ſay, that muſt be Reaſon: This is an Extravagancy in which no Authority upon Earth can bear a Man out. For if a Profeſſor, when he is preſs'd by ſome Untoward Objections againſt ſome Opinion he has deliver'd, ſhould think fit to anſwer only with his Brow, or elſe to deliver it again as his poſitive Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment out of the Chair, declaring, That it belonged to him to dictate in that place; I am apt to believe that his Beard, though never ſo venerable, would ſcarce be able to preſerve him from the Contempt and Deriſion of his own Diſciples. Or if a Judge, queſtion'd for an Unjuſt Sentence, ſhould inſtead of Law or Equity, produce only his Commiſſion, to juſtifie his Act; I am afraid whatever became of his Perſon, his Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation would be in ſome danger: Eſpecially if all were of Judge<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ruſtworth</hi>'s Coll. T. 1. P. 506.</note> 
               <hi>Dodridg</hi>'s mind, <q>That it is no more fit for a Judge to decline to give an Account of his Doings, than for a Chriſtian of his Faith.</q> Now this is the Caſe between Us and the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> We charge Them of Corrupting the Faith, of Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Superſtition, and Inſufferable Tyranny: We pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce our Evidence, and alledge Scripture and Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Antiquity to make out Our Charge. On the other ſide, She takes upon her, and ſtands upon her Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege; She defines and proves it with a Curſe, which is a Spiritual kind of Hectoring, and We are Hereticks convict, becauſe we are not ſatisfied with theſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations. For my own part, I think they are to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98083:11"/>blame that do not like this Proceeding in an Enemy; for the neareſt thing to an Acknowledgment that the <hi>Roman</hi> Cauſe is Indefenſible, is this deſperate way of maintaining it; the leſs of Argument Men have, the more Poſitive they grow, and endeavour to make up their want of Reaſon by the Boldneſs and Peremptori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Affirmation: And though ſome may aſcribe the Infallibility-ſhift to the Confidence of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I ſhall rather impute it to her Deſperation. And we are the more confirmed in this Suſpicion, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church was brought to this Shift by Diſtreſs, rather than Choice, when we conſider the time and the Occaſion upon which we find her open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to have declared her ſelf Infallible. When the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Church quarrell'd with thoſe of the <hi>West,</hi> about ſome Points of Doctrin, as well as Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Obſervances; among other things, they urge, That the Catholick Church was on their Side. For of the five Patriarchs which Govern'd the Church, whom they uſually compar'd to the five Senſes, there were four for the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Opinions: And if two to one be accounted odds, it will be intolerable Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for one to oppoſe four. For ſo <hi>Michael Ceru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larius</hi> urges, not intending to confer any Infallibility upon thoſe four Patriarchs, but from a Majority plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Preſumption of Right. Pope <hi>Leo</hi> oppoſes to this the Dignity of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and the Privilege which the <hi>Roman</hi> Church had of being Infallible, though ſhe ſtood alone. This appears by the Letters of <hi>Michael,</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and <hi>Leo</hi> the Ninth's Reply to their Objections; and it is no wonder the Pope took Sanctuary in ſuch a Pretence, when Authority did commonly bear down Reaſon: And the <hi>Roman</hi> Church was too great to depend upon
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98083:11"/>the ſole Merit of the Cauſe, and ſuch Reaſons as were common to her with every private Chriſtian in the World. But this Pretence of Infallibility was yet ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Inſinuated than Defined, till <hi>Gregory</hi> VII. (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd and depos'd by ſeveral <hi>German</hi> and <hi>Italian</hi> Councils) was forc'd to lift up his See beyond all Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man meaſure, and to declare poſitively, That his Church could never Err. About an Hundred and fifty Years after this, the Schoolmen invented the Term <hi>Infallibility,</hi> to expreſs this Unaccountable Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege. Mr. <hi>Creſſy</hi> calls it an Unfortunate Word; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is indeed: For never any had harder uſage than this. It is forced to ſtand againſt Scripture and Tradition, againſt Authority, and Reaſon, and Senſe: This poor Infallibility muſt hide all Faults, muſt cover every Defect, and vouch every Abſurdity, and juſtifie even Tranſubſtantiation.</p>
            <p>I have inſiſted I fear too long upon the grounds we may have to ſuſpect, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> does not really believe her own Infallibility. What con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit ſhe may have of her ſelf, or how ſhe may ſtand in the Opinion of her Adherents, is to us of no great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, ſince we do not conceive our ſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, either by her fond Fancies of her own Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, or the extravagant Applauſes of her Flatterers; only we would deſire ſhe would not preſs us too vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently to this Belief, while ſhe is under ſuch flagrant Suſpicion of Deriding it within her ſelf. If ſhe do really believe this, we envy her not the Paradiſe of ſuch a Conceit; but rather pity her Diſeaſe, and the diſorder of her Imagination, for ſo it is. And ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing not unlike her caſe we have in the Character of the Church of <hi>Laodicea; Becauſe thou hast ſaid, I am Rich, and encreaſed with Goods, and have need of nothing, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98083:12"/>knoweſt not that thou art Wretched, and Miſerable, and Poor, and Blind, and Naked; anoint thine Eyes with Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalve, that thou mayeſt ſee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But be the <hi>Roman</hi> Pretence never ſo ſincere, we have further grounds of Suſpicion, that really there is no ſuch thing. For,</p>
            <p n="1">I. Chriſt himſelf, the Author of our Faith, though he was Infallible becauſe he was God, yet did not think fit to uſe this way of Authority or meer De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining, to introduce his Doctrin, nor to recommend it to his Diſciples as a Principle for trying Doctr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, when he was gone to Heaven. The way therefore which our Saviour took, was to Prove and to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince by Arguments proper and concluſive: When he was queſtion'd, he appeal'd to the Scriptures, <hi>Search the Scriptures, for they teſtifie of me. If I bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my ſelf, my witneſs is not true.</hi> And therefore produces the Teſtimony of <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptist,</hi> of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at his Baptiſm, of the Miracles that he did, <hi>The ſame Works which I do, they bear witneſs of me that the Father hath ſent me. — If ye do not believe me, believe the Works.</hi> But above all, he alledges the Scripture in Vindication of his Perſon and his Doctrin. When he was blamed for Healing on the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> he juſtifies himſelf from the Law that permitted Beaſts to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved on that day, and by an Argument <hi>a fortiori,</hi> he proves, That a Charity towards a Child of <hi>Abraham</hi> was much more to be allowed. When the <hi>Sadducees</hi> diſputed with him, he reproach'd them for <hi>not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures,</hi> but blames them not at all for being ignorant of the Infallible Judge. In ſhort, all his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, all his Preaching, all his Diſputes, were full of Arguments and Proofs drawn from the Merits of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98083:12"/>the Cauſe, from Scripture and Reaſon; and to finiſh his Evidence, and the Conviction of his Hearers, often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he crown'd all with Miracles. The <hi>Phariſees</hi> indeed, when they were at a loſs for an Argument, would take Refuge in their Authority; and therefore when they could not anſwer a poor Man, thus they take upon them, <hi>Thou wast altogether born in Sin, and dost thou Teach us? Are we blind alſo? And have any of the Phariſees believed on him?</hi> But our Saviour, inſtead of Encouraging this aſſuming way, warns his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples againſt it; <hi>Call no Man Rabbi or Maſter upon Earth; call no Man Father; i.e.</hi> Submit not your ſelves implicitly to ſuch Arrogant Teachers as theſe, that uſurp Dominion over your Faith. And therefore he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commends to Men the Uſe of their Judgment, <hi>Why of your own ſelves judge ye not what is right?</hi> And leſt any ſhould think that this noble Faculty was given them only for their Worldly Occaſions, he reproaches the <hi>Jews</hi> for not making due Uſe of it in Enquiries of Religion, <hi>Ye can diſcern the face of the Heaven, and why do you not diſcern this time</hi> of the <hi>Meſſiah;</hi> Which the Scriptures did plainly mark out to thoſe that would uſe their Judgment to diſcern them. Now it became our Saviour to deal with us in this manner; for ſince upon our account he was pleas'd to be made Man, it was moſt ſuitable to that Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion to ſpeak to us as a Man, and to meet us in our own way of Apprehenſion. And beſides it ſeems more agreeable to the Nature of the Eternal Word or Reaſon, to ſatisfie and convince our Underſtandings, than to amaze and confound them with Paradoxes without Proof or Explanation. Although Chriſt's Diſciples call'd him Maſter, and ſo indeed he was; yet he did not uſe them as Servants, but as Friends; <hi>For the Servant
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98083:13"/>knows not what his Lord doth:</hi> A Servant is not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Reaſons, or to know the Intention of his Maſter in every thing he commands. But Chriſt calls his Diſciples Friends, becauſe <hi>he had made known to them all things that he had heard of the Father.</hi> Beſides, it is much cheaper to affirm Confidently, than to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any tolerable Proof; and many may amaze Men with ſtrange and extravagant Opinions, that are not able to render any Reaſon that may move an ordinary, ſober Underſtanding. The <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> and the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant Sects that ſprung from them, would ſubmit their wild Conceits to no rational Examination; you muſt take all upon their Credit, or be an Infidel. For theſe Myſtical <hi>Rabbies</hi> were above the poor Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of giving Reaſons. <hi>Apelles</hi> the Heretick, in a Conference with <hi>Rhodon,</hi> affirms, That a Man ought not to Examine his Faith, but to content himſelf with whatever Opinion he had receiv'd: And being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded a Proof for his Belief of One God, ſince he rejected <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets.</hi> He frankly confeſs'd He had none to give, but that he was mov'd, he knew not how, to believe it: And therefore is juſtly derided by his Antagoniſt. But the true Chriſtians did not thus learn Chriſt; they received his Doctrin not only becauſe he Pronounced it, but becauſe he gave Proof and Demonſtration of what he ſaid. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the outward Teſtimony of Miracles, it was no ſmall help to their Conviction, to ſee the Inward Merit and Excellency of this Religion, that it had nothing unworthy of God, nothing contrary to Moral Honeſty, or the Principles of Natural Religion. And <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> though he believed in Chriſt with ſo much Aſſurance as to Die for him; yet to let us ſee that his Faith was not altogether Implicit, but ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98083:13"/>upon Rational Conviction from the Merit of the Doctrin, makes this bold and ſomewhat harſh Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, in his Book againſt <hi>Marcion; That he ſhould not have believed Chriſt himſelf, had he preach'd any other God beſide the Creator.</hi> And we have <hi>Irenaeus</hi>'s Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, That <hi>it was well ſaid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtles did not think fit to make uſe of this way of Infallibility, though the Promiſe upon which it is now grounded was made immediately to them; and the Aſſiſtance of the Spirit was viſible in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles they wrought. But they did not affect to be above their Maſter, and they could not forget that Caution he gave them, Not to be call'd of Men <hi>Rabbies.</hi> Nay, ſo far were they from affecting Dominion over the Faith and Underſtanding of Chriſtians, that they permit and applaud the diligence of thoſe, who would not receive the Goſpel upon their bare Affirmation, but <hi>ſearch'd the Scriptures, to ſee whether thoſe things were ſo</hi> as they were alledged by the Apoſtles: If we may allow St. <hi>Luke</hi> to ſpeak their ſenſe. It was St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Advice to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that they ſhould <hi>Examine themſelves whether they were in the Faith;</hi> and he renounces <hi>all Dominion over their Faith.</hi> When the ſame <hi>Corinthians</hi> doubted of the Reſurrection, St. <hi>Paul</hi> does not think it ſufficient to ſay, That it was defined, and a received Article of the Creed: But enters into the Merits of the Cauſe, and proves the Truth by Arguments unanſwerable, and Defends it againſt all the Objections that had rendred it ſuſpected. When the Churches of <hi>Galatia</hi> were divided upon the great Queſtion, Whether the <hi>Gentile</hi> Chriſtians were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged toobſerve the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Moſes;</hi> and many pretended the Authority of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>James</hi> to the Prejudice of Chriſtian Liberty; St. <hi>Paul</hi> undertakes our Defence, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98083:14"/>throws off all, not only the Authority of Men, though they were Apoſtles, but of Angels; <hi>Though an Angel from Heaven ſhould preach any other Goſpel, let him be accurſed:</hi> And this high Declaration was intended, if <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> underſtand it right, to ſhew, <hi>That where the Debate is concerning Truth, St.</hi> Paul <hi>will not be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with the Dignity or Office of any Perſons;</hi> As if that muſt be Goſpel which they declare. Alas then for the Infallible Judge, if there be no reſpect of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, no regard of Offices, when Truth is in queſtion! We were told a quite contrary ſtory, That the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way to know the Truth, was to conſult Men plac'd in certain Dignities, and to take for Oracle whatſoever they ſhall think fit to define. St. <hi>Paul,</hi> it ſeems, knew nothing of any Infallible Judge, from the heavenly Angels downwards; and <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> his Interpreter, takes not the leaſt care to Except him. The <hi>Greeks</hi> have a Tradition, That when <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> wrote his Comments upon St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, the Apoſtle was ſeen for ſeveral days ſtanding behind the Biſhop's Chair, and whiſpering into his Ear: But without believing this, a Man may have reaſon to be ſatisfied, that the <hi>Gloſs</hi> ſpeaks the ſenſe of the Text; and if all his Epiſtles had been as clear as this Paſſage, I am apt to believe that this Apoſtle might have ſav'd himſelf the labour of coming down from Heaven to be his own Commentator. I muſt confeſs, that in reading this Epiſtle, I have often wondred how St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould come to omit one Argument, which, according to the Men of the Infallible way, muſt have been worth all the reſt: And that is, the Determination of this Queſtion by the Council of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> for all are agreed, and the Notation of years which we find in the Firſt and Second Chapters, makes it clear, that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98083:14"/>this Epiſtle was written after that Council; yet in all this long Vindication of the Liberty of the <hi>Gentile</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, it is not once urg'd. And I cannot conceive any reaſon of this Omiſſion, unleſs it be that having in the very beginning laid aſide all Human Authority, and Reſpect of Perſons, he might not think it proper afterwards to alledge the Apoſtolical Decree: But if this had been the only Infallible way of Deciding Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, this Omiſſion cannot be excuſed. Now becauſe ſome have endeavoured to prove the Infallibility of Councils, from the Example of that of the Apoſtles, I proceed briefly to ſhew, That they did not proceed in the way of Infallibility, though they were really In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, becauſe they were Inſpired Perſons; but all their Proceeding was according to Allegation and Proof, and the Concluſion is made to depend upon theſe Premiſſes, and not their Infallibility in pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing it. Whereas in the New Way, the Concluſion is Certain, becauſe ſome Men declare it, though the Reaſons alledged may be good for nothing: The ſumm of that Synodical Action was this; Firſt S. <hi>Peter</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to them, How the Holy Ghoſt had already De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined that Queſtion, by falling upon <hi>Cornelius</hi> and other Perſons Uncircumciſed; then <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> declared, <hi>What Wonders that God had wrought among the Gentiles by them.</hi> And laſtly, S. <hi>James</hi> ſhews out of the Prophets, How the Converſion of the Gentiles was foretold; and concludes, <hi>Wherefore my Sentence is</hi>— Then it pleaſed the Apoſtles and Elders to ſend certain Perſons with an account of this whole Matter, to the Churches concerned; and a Letter with this Expreſſion, among others, <hi>It ſeemed Good to the Holy Ghoſt and to us:</hi> Which does not import as if whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they agreed to declare muſt therefore be the Truth,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98083:15"/>and to be received without asking farther Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, though what they did Decree was certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Truth and Right; but only ſuggeſts the former Deciſion of the Holy Ghoſt, in the Caſe of <hi>Cornelius;</hi> and ſome other declared by <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Paul;</hi> for then it ſeemed Good to the Holy Ghoſt to receive the Gentiles without Circumciſion. But in the Aſſembly of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> we have not the leaſt Intimation of any Declaration of the Spirit, either by Miracle or Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But the Holy Ghoſt having before viſibly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared upon the Point, to that in all likelihood the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion muſt allude. But whatever the Apoſtles thought of the way of Infallibility, it is plain, The Believers were not yet well inſtructed concerning it; for this Definition could not end the Controverſie. And in the beginning of the next Chapter, We find S. <hi>Paul</hi> Circumciſing <hi>Timothy,</hi> whoſe Father was a <hi>Greek, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Jews that were in thoſe Quarters,</hi> and how little Uſe was made of it in ending the ſame Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie in the Church of <hi>Galatia,</hi> I have obſerved al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. But further yet; S. <hi>Paul,</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> teaches another Method of Belief than the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates for Infallibility, for ſome time would impoſe upon the World; for he utterly diſallows this way of making the Faith of God to depend upon the Belief or Unbelief of Men, as if that were to be the Standard of Truth and Error: <hi>For what if ſome did not Believe? ſhall their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief make the Faith of God of none Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect? God forbid! Yea let God be True and every Man a Lyar, as it is written,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This is an Anſwer to ſuch Objections as were Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted againſt the Chriſtian Faith, from the Unbelief of the Jews. For when our Saviour appeared, they had the Viſible Church, and all Eccleſiaſtical Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98083:15"/>the Prieſthood, the Sanadrim, the Scribes and Phariſees, and the Renowned Doctors were theirs, the Religious Sects, the Outward Purity, the <hi>Opus operatum,</hi> and Supererogation were on their Side. Now if theſe muſt preſcribe to our Belief, we Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans have loſt our Cauſe; for the High Prieſt and the Elders aſſembled, <hi>i. e.</hi> The Pope and Council of that Time condemned Chriſt for a Blaſphemer. But S. <hi>Paul</hi> would no more ſubmit to ſuch Definitions, than we Proteſtants to thoſe of the <hi>Council of Trent,</hi> but enters his Proteſtation againſt all ſuch as by any Act of Men would Preſcribe againſt the Truth of God, and gives Reaſon and Scripture for his Proceeding; God muſt be Pure, but all Men may be Lyars; and ſo fairly takes his leave of all Infallible Men. And ſo far is he from Affecting that Brerogative himſelf, which he denies to others, that he appeals to the Scriptures, as his Vouchers, and does not deſire to be believed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Authority of his Place, but by the Method he uſes of proving what he advances, he ſets a Fair Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent to all other Teachers, and which <hi>Origen,</hi> upon this Place, underſtands to be his Deſign. <hi>For if a Perſon ſo Great and ſo Qualifyed as S.</hi> Paul, <hi>did not think the Authority of his Saying any thing to be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, unleſs he prove it out of the Law and the Prophets; how much more ſhould we, the leaſt of Gods Miniſters, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſame Rule?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Laſtly, S. <hi>Peter,</hi> from whom ſome of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitors for Infallibility derive their Title, adviſes all Chriſtians, <hi>To be ready always to give an anſwer to every one that asketh them a Reaſon of the Hope that is in them.</hi> Now all Interpreters of this Place, both Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and Modern, that I have ſeen, are very much out, if this Reaſon be no other than the Infallibility of S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:98083:16"/>or of the Church: Now this Anſwer, <hi>I Believe becauſe the Church Believes,</hi> is ſurely the Eaſieſt of any, and all other Anſwers would be Impertinent, if this alone were the Infallible Reaſon: The School-Men have upon ſome Occaſions thought fit to ground their Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Way upon this Paſſage, and Valued their Uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Service to the Church on this Account. But for God's ſake, What Uſe can there be of theſe Fallible Reaſons in a Church that is Infallible in her Concluſions, and holds not her ſelf obliged to render any other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for them but a Curſe? And indeed I cannot ſee any Occaſion of giving any Reaſon, ſince her Diſciples do Profeſs that they have no Aſſurance, but that in theſe ſhe may be Miſtaken.</p>
            <p>Now if the Apoſtles did not think fit to uſe this Way of Infallibility, it ſeems ſomething incongruous for the Church in Succeeding Ages to pretend to it; for as the Gifts of the Spirit grew leſs, methinks the Way of Teaching ſhould rather be leſs than more Magiſterial; unleſs ſome new Paraclet, to ſupply the Defect of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles and Inſpiration, had thought fit to confer upon it the Gift of Infallible Deciſion: But the Generation next to the Apoſtles knew nothing of this Matter, but Confeſs the State of the Church in their Time to be Inferiour to that of the Apoſtolick Age, and that Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks then could not be ſo effectually Suppreſſed, as they were by the Apoſtles and immediate Diſciples of our Saviour. For <hi>Hegeſyppus,</hi> ſpeaking of the Martyrdom of <hi>Symeon</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> obſerves, That to that Time the Church had continued a Virgin and Unpollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; for while the Apoſtles lived, Hereticks were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to keep themſelves cloſe; but when their Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was cloſed, then theſe Deceivers began to appear with wonderful Confidence. What abſurd Fellows
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98083:16"/>were theſe to think They could prevail againſt an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Church at one Time more than another; had they no Dread of the Infallible Judge? Did they not know that his Sentence could make them Hereticks Convict, when ever he thought fit to pronounce it; or at leaſtwiſe, Did they not know that all Chriſtians Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved ſuch a Judge? and therefore could have as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Hopes then, as in the Time of the Apoſtles. But though we let theſe paſs for Impudent Stupid Fellows; Yet what ſhould this <hi>Hegeſyppus</hi> mean by Repreſenting the Church as a Virgin but to ſuch a Time, ſince in deſpight of all Hereſies the Church muſt always re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main Pure and Uncorrupted? <hi>Valeſius</hi> would fain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer this to the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> only: But he inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly Confeſſes, That <hi>Euſebius</hi> who Cites it, meant otherwiſe, and applyed it to the Church in General: And the Reaſons that <hi>Hegeſyppus</hi> gives, make it plain that ſo he meant it too. And therefore <hi>Valeſius</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeaks a favourable Interpretation of them both. How little Thought <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> and <hi>Irenaeus</hi> had of this Way of Infallibility I have mentioned before, they both Wrote againſt Hereſies, and <hi>Irenaeus</hi> his Books are ſtill Extant; but not the leaſt Mention made of the Authority of the Infallible Judge; Scripture and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Senſe furniſh all his Arguments. Tradition, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, is once mentioned, becauſe Hereticks made this their Pretence; but then too it is uſed only for a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Argument, to ſhew that the Apoſtolick Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches never Taught any ſuch Traditionary Doctrines, without the leaſt Pretence that thoſe Churches had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived any other Articles of Belief beſides what were contained in the Scripture. <hi>Clemens</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> lays down ſeveral Ways of Detecting Hereticks, but it was his Misfortune, or rather that of his Age, to be Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98083:17"/>of that which is now accounted the only Infallible. <hi>Tertullian</hi> Preſcribes againſt all Hereticks, without troubling the Scriptures, from the Common Rule of Faith, which is not an Indefinite One in <hi>petto,</hi> but a ſhort Summary of the chief Points of Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, from the Novelty of Hereſies, from the Doctrine of Apoſtolical Churches, Founded before thoſe Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Sprung. But his Misfortune is not only to omit the Infallible Judge, but to preclude him in the very Beginning of his Book by this Remarkable Paſſage: <hi>What then</hi> (ſays he) <hi>if a Biſhop, or a Deacon, or a Widow, or a Virgin; nay if a Martyr or a Doctor ſhould fall from the Rule, muſt Hereſie therefore be Truth? What do we receive Doctrines for the ſake of Perſons, or Perſons for the ſake of Doctrines?</hi> But how ſhall we know Truth from Hereſie, if we may not depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Perſon of the Infallible Judge? And do not thoſe who reſolve their Doctrine into the Definition of an Infallible Judge, approve the Doctrine for the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Sake?<note place="margin">Orig. <hi>contra</hi> Celſ. <hi>l.</hi> 3.</note> When <hi>Celſus</hi> Reproached the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans with their Diviſions, and Multitude of their Sects, <hi>Origen</hi> had no better Reply to make, than, That this Misfortune was not peculiar to them, for the ſame thing happened to Phyſicians and Philoſophers, and yet to Wiſe Men it was no Prejudice againſt thoſe Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. And then ſhews how theſe Sects ſprung from their different Underſtanding of the Scripture; but could not, it ſeems, think of the Remedy which was peculiar to them, and of an Infallible Judge, and that therefore, thoſe who rejected his Definitions, were inexcuſable, and unworthy of the Name of Chriſtians. But <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> on <hi>Acts</hi> 15, draws this Anſwer to the Point, when he declares, <hi>That Chriſtians had no other way of chuſing their Church, in this variety of Chriſtian
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98083:17"/>Sects, than Phyſicians or Philoſophers had in determining what Sect they ſhould follow:</hi> Which was no other than uſing their beſt Judgment and Diligence in the Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Common Rule. But <hi>Lactantius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De vera Sap. l. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> for want of Knowing this Infallible Judge, gives the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Direction of any to diſcern the true Faith, in the midſt of Different Pretenſions. <hi>The Catholick Church,</hi> ſays he, <hi>alone has the True Religion:</hi> If he had ſtuck here, we might have thought, perhaps, that he had known the Myſtery of Infallibility; but when he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds a little further, he ſpoils all: <hi>Hereticks,</hi> ſays he, <hi>pretend to have the Catholick Church as well as the Truth.</hi> His Anſwer to the Objection follows, <hi>That thoſe have the Catholick Church who have Confeſſion and Penance, and that Heals thoſe Sins and Wounds to which Human Frailty is ſubject.</hi> The Good Man at that Time hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to think of the <hi>Montaniſts</hi> or <hi>Novatians,</hi> and therefore deſcribes the True Church in Oppoſition to their Severity, to be that which reſtored Penitent Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to Communion, after Publick Confeſſion of their Fault, and publick Satisfaction to the Church. But, by this Rule, how ſhall we know the True Church in the Controverſie between the <hi>Catholicks</hi> and the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> for they were both agreed in this Point of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline? But how can we expect that theſe Writers before the <hi>Nicene Council,</hi> ſhould ſay much of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Judge; ſince ſhe had no ſuch, if either a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Council alone, or in conjunction with the Pope be it? for it is well known, That from the Time of the Apoſtles to the Synod of <hi>Nice,</hi> there was no General Council. And <hi>Alphonſus a Caſtro</hi> imputes the Number and Extravagance of the Hereſies of thoſe Times to the Want of an Infallible Judge,<note place="margin">Adv. Hereſ. l. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> which he takes to be a General Council. But I cannot get this Scruple out
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98083:18"/>of my Head, How God ſhould intend ſuch a Judge, as the only certain Means of Preſerving the Integrity of Chriſtian Religion againſt Hereſie, and yet ſuffer his Church to be without it for almoſt three Ages, when ſhe ſtood in the greateſt Need of ſuch a Help, and was otherwiſe by her Holineſs and Glorious Martyrdoms, beſt qualifyed to receive ſuch an Extraordinary Favour: And afterwards, when the Emperours were Chriſtian and Orthodox, there ſeemed to be leſs Need of it, for their Laws againſt Hereticks might perhaps be more Infallible in their Effect of Suppreſſing them, than the moſt ſolemn Sentence of the Infallible Judge. For the Popes of thoſe Ages, though they were ingaged in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Controverſies, yet neither did they pretend to be Infallible, nor were they acknowledged as ſuch by any other Churches. The Diſpute between Pope <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen</hi> and S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> about Rebaptizing, is well known, and whoever compares their Opinions with what the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> Determined upon that Queſtion, will find they were both in the Wrong.<note place="margin">Tertul. <hi>adv.</hi> Prax.</note> Pope <hi>Anicetus</hi> gave but a poor Sign of his Infallibility, when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Prophecy's of <hi>Montanus, Priſca</hi> and <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milla,</hi> and received the <hi>Aſiaticks</hi> and <hi>Cataphrygians</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Communion: And <hi>Marcellinus</hi> his Infallibility muſt ſurely forſake him, when he offered Incenſe to Idols, as the <hi>Roman Offices</hi> do accuſe him; and though <hi>Baronius</hi> mentions the Endeavours of ſome Zealous Men to take off this Blemiſh, yet after all the Reviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Breviary,</hi> it remains there ſtill.</p>
            <p>But be the Catholick Church, before the <hi>Nicene Council</hi> as deſtitute of Infallible Judgment as it was of Civil Force, ſurely when Councils were aſſembled, with the concurrence of Popes, all Diſpute and Hereſie muſt be at an end; for when the Infallible Judge has
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98083:18"/>taken his Place, all Knots in Religion muſt be Unty'd, and all Doubts removed, for who ſo Ignorant or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, as to diſpute againſt his Sentence, whom all the Chriſtian World muſt know to be uncapable of Miſtake? Now the Misfortune is, That after Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny General Councils, received by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the greateſt part of Chriſtendom, we hear no Tydings of an Infallible Judge, nor of the <hi>Roman</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of Faith into the meer Authority of Papal Councils: And this is ſuch a Diſappointment, under which no Man can be patient, and in ſpight of all Good Diſpoſition of Believing the Roman Method, it will breed Suſpicion, That the Infallible was not revealed to the Church of thoſe Times. <hi>Athanaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> the great Champion and Confeſſor for the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene Creed,</hi> in all his Apologies, forgot this great and unanſwerable Defence, That he followed an Infallible Guide. He Explains and Confirms from Scripture,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Athan.</hi> or. ad <hi>Maxim.</hi> Id. de <hi>Nicen.</hi> Synod. Decret. Orat. <hi>1.</hi> contr. <hi>Arrian.</hi>
               </note> the Notion of Conſubſtantial; but could not be ſo happy as to urge, That it muſt be true, Becauſe the Infallible had pronounc'd it. He deſervedly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends the <hi>Nicene Council,</hi> and the Faith defined there; but his Reaſons turn Infallibility upſide down: For he received the Determination of that great Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly; becauſe in his Judgment he was convinc'd, That it was True, and Conſonant to the Scriptures, but did not therefore think, It muſt be as True as Goſpel, Becauſe it was the Sentence of an Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Judge. And, at laſt, in the Way of our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Reſolution of Faith, declares, That in thoſe Controverſies that divided the Church, <hi>We ought to pray for the Spirit of Diſcretion, That every one may know what to Receive and what to Reject: A Faithful Diſciple of the Goſpel is able to diſtinguiſh between Truth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98083:19"/>and Pretence, becauſe he has the Spirit of Diſcerning; but the Simple is carryed away with every Colour.</hi> But what ſhould we do with this Private Spirit of Diſcretion, in a Controverſie already decided by the Infallible? And what danger of the Simple, if he can but be Simple enough, to Believe as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Infallible Church Believes? And it is yet more ſtrange, That after the <hi>Nicene Deciſions</hi> this Father ſhould recommend the Scriptures as a better and <hi>more ſufficient</hi> Means than any other for our Direction to the True Faith.<note place="margin">Con. <hi>Maxim.</hi> l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> was ſurely to blame, when in a Diſpute with an <hi>Arrian,</hi> he makes this Propoſal, That they ſhould by Conſent lay aſide the Authority of Council-Definitions, and gives up the Judgment of the <hi>Nicene Fathers,</hi> in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change for that of the Hereticks of <hi>Rimini,</hi> and leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Advantage of a Sentence, by which alone the Truth could be Infallibly known, according to the <hi>Roman Suppoſition,</hi> deſcends to put the Matter upon an Iſſue, which we are now told, is very uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and of dangerous Conſequence; that is, To be tryed by Scripture and Reaſon. One would think it had been a much eaſier and ſhorter Task for him to prove the <hi>Council of Nice</hi> Infallible, if he had thought it as Demonſtrable as the Miſſionaries ſay it is, than to convince the Hereticks by Diſputable Paſſages of Scripture, interpreted according to his Private Reaſon: Here indeed he overthrows Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility, but Implicitly and by Conſequence; but in another place he expreſly Diſclaims it: <hi>The Church,</hi> ſays he,<note place="margin">L. <hi>2.</hi> con. <hi>Creſcon.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ought not to ſet her ſelf above Chriſt: — for he always Judges according to Truth, but Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Judges, as Men, are commonly-Miſtaken.</hi> And then, leſt you may imagine General Councils ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98083:19"/>in another place he declares, That even <hi>Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Councils</hi> may need Amendment; and that,<note place="margin">L. <hi>2.</hi> de Bapt. c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The latter may Correct what is Amiſs in the former.</hi> And in an Epiſtle to S. <hi>Jerom,</hi> he further declares, <hi>That he had learned to pay this Deference only to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical Scriptures, of believing their Authors to have erred in nothing. But others, though never ſo Learned or Holy</hi> (without any Exception) <hi>I read ſo, as not to take any thing to be True, becauſe they were of that Opinion, but becauſe they proved it by Scripture or Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S. <hi>Jerom</hi> profeſſes ſo firm adherence to his Private Coviction,<note place="margin">Ep. ad <hi>Auguſt.</hi> Apud <hi>Flac. Illyr.</hi> in Cato l. Teſt. &amp; Suttliv. de Eccleſ.</note> That the Authority of all the World ſhould never be able to make him depart from it. <hi>This,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I affirm, this I boldly pronounce, though all the World ſhould gainſay it:</hi> And he makes no Scruple of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting Councils, if they determine any thing againſt the Doctrine of the Scriptures;<note place="margin">In <hi>Eſai.</hi> c. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> nay he makes it the Character of Hereticks, <hi>That they take upon them ſo great Authority, That whether they Teach Truth or Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood, they will not allow their Diſciples to examine by Reaſon, but Implicitly to follow their Leaders:</hi> And yet I do not know of any of theſe arrived to ſuch an Extravagance as to pronounce themſelves Infallible.<note place="margin">Nazianz. <hi>ep. ad</hi> Procop.</note> 
               <hi>Gregory</hi> the Divine was ſurely a Stranger to the Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Judge, when he reſolves <hi>to ſhun all Aſſemblies of Biſhops, becauſe he never ſaw Good Iſſue of any of them.</hi> And I can ſcarce believe that he would have been con tent to ſubmit the Faith to Major Vote,<note place="margin">Orat. ad <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian.</hi>
               </note> when he brings in the <hi>Arrians inſulting over the little Flock of Chriſt, defining the Church by Multitude, and preferring the Sand to the Stars.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. Antioch. <hi>in Conc.</hi> Epheſ. <hi>t.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 70. <hi>&amp;</hi> 76. <hi>Ed.</hi> Labbe.</note> He muſt needs be Ignorant of the Infallible Judge, that thus writes to the Emperor <hi>Theodoſius</hi> againſt <hi>Cyril</hi> and his <hi>Epheſin Council; That
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98083:20"/>a great number of Biſhops is unneceſſary for the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of Opinions in Religion, and ſerves only to create Tumults: For this End our Adverſaries bring great Numbers, depending only upon that, and not upon the Truth and Orthodoxneſs of their Belief:</hi> And then ſpeaking of <hi>Cyril, Endeavouring to ratifie his Hereſie by Multitude, not conſidering, That in Religion, it is not Number that is required, but Orthodox Faith, and the Truth of Apoſtolick Doctrine.</hi> And it is ſtrange, in all the Diſputes between <hi>Cyril</hi> and <hi>Theodoret</hi> there is not the leaſt Word about the Infallible Definition of the <hi>Epheſin Synod;</hi> which had decided the Matter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Diſpute: And it is no ſmall Prejudice againſt the Infallible Way;<note place="margin">Cyril. <hi>Ep. ad</hi> Euopt.</note> that <hi>Cyril</hi> tells his Adverſary, <hi>That he ought to Argue out of the Scriptures only.</hi> There was never Council occaſioned more Diſpute than that of <hi>Chalcedon;</hi> the World was a long while divided about it: But thoſe who declare their Adherence to it, never pretend it to have been Infallible; but on the contrary,<note place="margin">Ep. <hi>Anatol.</hi> ad <hi>Leon.</hi> Ep. Epiſcop. <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rop.</hi> ad <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> &amp; Epiſc. Iſaur. ad eund. vid. Tom. <hi>5.</hi> Conc. Ed. <hi>Labb.</hi>
               </note> Profeſs their Approbation of it, <hi>Becauſe it had Aſſerted the True Faith;</hi> not that the Faith muſt be true becauſe aſſerted by it; becauſe it had <hi>defined nothing New or Strange againſt the Rectitude of the Faith;</hi> becauſe it had <hi>added nothing to the Faith, or altered nothing in the Conſtitutions of former Councils, or explained any thing Incongruouſly, but followed the Scripture and the</hi> Nicene Council.<note place="margin">Ep. <hi>Syriae 2.</hi> ibid.</note> And the Biſhops of <hi>Syria</hi> declare their Opinion not only of this, but of all the other received General Councils, <hi>That they Decree them to be True Councils, becauſe they have Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted and Ratified this Faith by the Holy Seriptures.</hi> What ſhall we call this but a Proteſtant Rule of Faith, when a Council is to be known to be True or Falſe from its Doctrine, and not the Doctrine from the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98083:20"/>Infallibility of the Judge? And <hi>Maximus,</hi> it ſeems,<note place="margin">Collat. S. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximi</hi> cum <hi>Theodoſ.</hi> Ep. <hi>Caeſar.</hi> Ed. <hi>Sirm.</hi> p. <hi>161, 162.</hi>
               </note> had no other Means of diſcerning True from Errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Councils, but the Doctrine they defined: <hi>For</hi> (ſays he) <hi>If the Emperor's Summons or Commands, give Authority to Synods, and not the True Faith; receive the Synods that have been aſſembled againſt the Word Conſubſtantial:</hi> And having reckoned up many Heretical Councils, concludes, <hi>But they were all condemned for the Impiety of their Erroneous Opinions confirmed by them</hi>—And then, <hi>The Rule of the Church acknowledges thoſe for true Synods, which the Orthodoxneſs of their Opinions doth Recommend</hi>— And <hi>Theodoſius</hi> Anſwers, <hi>It is ſo as thou affirmeſt, It is Orthodoxneſs of Belief gives Credit and Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to Synods.</hi> I might purſue the ſame Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation through ſeveral other General Councils, which a conſiderable part of the Church believed to have actually miſtaken, but to which none for ſome Ages aſcribed the Prerogative of Infallibility; but thoſe in which I have inſtanced, being the Principal for Reputation and Authority, it is needleſs to obſerve the ſame thing of thoſe that followed: And the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers taking the Liberty of Judging Conciliary De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitions by the Rule of Faith, the Holy Scriptures, do plainly overthrow all Pretence of an Unaccount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, Infallible Way of Defining, preſumed to be above all Examination and Review, becauſe above all poſſibility of Miſtaking.</p>
            <p>Now as the Church was Ignorant of the Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Judge during the conjunction of Eaſt and Weſt, and the Opportunity of General Councils; ſo the Greek Church, after it was broken off from the Weſt, was altogether unacquainted with this Infallible Way, and when the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> began to aſſume to it
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98083:21"/>ſelf the Quality of Infallible, the Eaſtern Church Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted againſt it. And while they follow the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch <hi>Photius,</hi> they can never Reſolve their Faith in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any Human or Eccleſiaſtical Authority; for he has prevented all ſuch Pretences, by that ſtrong Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation he makes in his Epiſtle to the Biſhop of <hi>Aquileia;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Photii</hi> Ep. ad Ep. <hi>Aquil.</hi> in Auct. Biblioth. Patr. per <hi>Combef.</hi> p. <hi>535.</hi>
               </note> where, in anſwer to the Authority of the Fathers, touching the Proceſſion of the Holy Ghoſt, he ſaith: <hi>What, ſhould I deſcend ſo low, as to ſpeak concerning the number of thoſe that affirm this thing? though the whole Creation ſhould do it with onc Voice, none ſurely would leave the Inſtruction and Doctrine of the Creator to hearken to the Voice of the Creature, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting him that made it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, I cannot avoid ſuſpecting the <hi>Roman</hi> Infallibility, when I conſider not only, That no other Church pretends to it, but that no Hereſie or Sect of Chriſtians ever claimed it. Theſe did ſeldom come behind the Church in Aſſuming and Pretence, and commonly preſumed more upon their Authority, and what they wanted in Truth and Proof, they made up with Arrogance and the Poſitive Way. There is no other Principle into which Faith is uſed to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, but they endeavour to make their own: Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, Tradition, Miracles, Revelation, all theſe they boldly challenged; but this Aſſurance of Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility, we never find them to have uſurped; I am loath to aſcribe it to their Modeſty; it is more likely, they had no Example to provoke them, and they were not ſo Fortunate as to find out the Way themſelves to ſo bold a Pretence, unleſs we may imagine that they had a better Opinion of their Way, than to think it ſtood in need of ſo Miſerable a Subterfuge. So that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98083:21"/>the Impudence of this Pretence is peculiar to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and may ſerve as a more proper Note to diſtinguiſh it, than any of thoſe laid down by <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> But this is no note of Honour, but a Brand; for as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> corrupted it ſelf beyond all others in Doctrine and Worſhip, the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Judgment delivered her up to a Reprobate Senſe, that renders her incapable of Diſcerning or Reforming her Errours; this Preſumption, That ſhe is not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Miſtake, hanging perpetually like a Veil over her Eyes.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:98083:22"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed for</hi> James Adamſon, <hi>at the</hi> Angel <hi>and</hi> Crown <hi>in</hi> S. Paul's Church-Yard.</head>
            <list>
               <item>I. A Treatiſe of the Celibacy of the Clergy, wherein its Riſe and Progreſs are Hiſtorically conſidered. In <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. A Treatiſe proving Scripture to be the Rule of Faith; writ by <hi>Reginald Peacock,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> before the Reformation, about the Year 1450. In <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>III. Several Captious Queries concerning the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, firſt propoſed by Dean <hi>Manby</hi> (an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert) in <hi>Latin:</hi> And afterwards by <hi>T. W.</hi> in <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fully Anſwered by the late reverend and learned Dr. <hi>Clagett,</hi> Preacher to the Honourable Society of <hi>Grays-Inn,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to His Majeſty.</item>
               <item>IV. Two Diſcourſes of Purgatory, and Prayers for the Dead. In <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>V. The Preſent State of the Controverſie, between the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> Or an Account of the Books written on both Sides, in a Letter to a Friend. In <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VI. Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi>'s Book, called, <hi>The Religion of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants a ſafe Way to Salvation,</hi> made more generally uſeful by omitting Perſonal Conteſts, but inſerting whatſoever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the common Cauſe of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> or defends the <hi>Church of England,</hi> with an exact Table of Contents; and an <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> of ſome genuine Pieces of Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi>'s never before printed, <hi>viz.</hi> againſt the <hi>Infallibility</hi> of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, <hi>Tranſubſtantiation, Tradition,</hi> &amp;c. And an Account of what moved the Author to turn Papiſt, with his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of the ſaid Motives. In <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VII. <hi>Clementis epiſtolae duae ad Corinthos, interpretibus Patricio, Juneo, Gothifredo, Vandelino &amp; Joh. Bapt. Cotelerio; recenſuit &amp; notarum ſpicilegium adjecit Paulus Colomeſius, bibliothecae Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bethanae curator; accedit Tho. Brunonici Windſorienſis diſſertatio de Therapeutis Philonis. His ſubnexae ſunt, epiſtolae aliquot ſingulares, vel nunc primum editae, vel non ita facile obviae.</hi> In <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VIII. The Travel, of <hi>Monſieur de Thevenot</hi> into the <hi>Levant;</hi> in Three Part, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Into <hi>Turky,</hi> 2. <hi>Perſia,</hi> 3. The <hi>Eaſt Indies.</hi> In <hi>Folio.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:98083:22"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
